Guide to the "Retracing Russell Lee" Project Collection
The Wittliff Collections
"Retracing Russell Lee" Project Collection
1991-1993
The Wittliff Collections
Carraro, Francine; Weller, Eric
SWWC.052
11 Linear Feet
16 boxes
This collection includes oral histories recorded on audio cassette tapes, transcriptions, videotapes, photographs, notes, and exhibit text panels which document this project, retracing FSA photographer Russell Lee's Depression era work in Pie Town, NM and San Augustine, TX.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Francine Carraro and Eric Weller, 1994
Project History
In July, 1991, a team of photographers and oral historians from Texas State University set out to retrace the steps of Farm Security Administration photographer, Russell Lee (1903-1986). Fifty years after Lee visited and photo-documented the living and working conditions of the Depression era communities of San Augustine, Texas, and Pie Town, New Mexico, this group was inspired by Lee's FSA images held at Texas State's Wittliff Collections. The group visited these same two towns Lee visited, in some cases the same people, taking photographs and conducting oral histories. The team was funded by a grant from the Ford Foundation, and was led by Francine Carraro and Eric Weller. Students included Tom Anderson, Kathleen Dolan, Homero Garcia, Kerri Madden, Darryl Meyer, Stephanie Shaddock, Karen Sorenson, Mark Edward Smith, Russell Smyth, and Sondra Talbert.
The oral histories and photographs taken by this team led to an exhibit and accompanying catalog featuring selected photographs and portions of the oral histories. The exhibit was first shown at Texas State in September, 1992, and traveled to Southern Methodist University (Dallas, TX) and Stephen F. Austin University (Nacogdoches, TX) in 1993.
Jean Lee, widow of Russell Lee, and Bill Wittliff donated a significant collection of Russell Lee's vintage FSA prints and field notes, as well as cameras, personal papers, and photographs spanning Lee's entire lifetime and career, to the Wittliff Collections beginning in 1986. While other institutions such as the Library of Congress, National Archives, University of Texas at Austin, and the University of Louisville also hold important Russell Lee collections, the collection at Texas State University includes the largest group of vintage FSA prints.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes oral histories recorded on audio cassette tapes, transcriptions, videotapes, photographs, notes, and exhibit text panels which document this project, retracing FSA photographer Russell Lee's Depression era work in Pie Town, NM and San Augustine, TX. Dates range from 1991-1993. The collection is arranged in five series: Oral Histories, Videotapes, Exhibit Catalog, Exhibit Panels, and Photographs.
Photography; Oral histories; Carraro, Francine; Weller, Eric; Lee, Russell, 1903-1986
- Oral Histories, 1991
  Series Description
  Oral Histories includes audiocassette tapes and transcriptions of oral histories taken by team members are arranged into Subseries A: Pie Town, New Mexico, and Subseries B: San Augustine, Texas. Under each town, materials are filed in alphabetical order by the name of the subject, with the audiocassette tapes first, followed by the transcripts. Most tapes have transcriptions, several do not.
  - Pie Town, New Mexico, 1991
    - Barney, Arden and Josie - Transcription, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Coon, Andy and Coonridge, Nancy (The Goat People) - Tape, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Coon, Andy and Coonridge, Nancy (The Goat People) - Transcription, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Crawford, Beatrice (also includes Don and Nita Kearbey) - Tapes (2), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hill, Mike - Tapes (3), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hill, Mike - Transcription, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hill, Mike and Chris - Tape, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Hill, Mike and Chris - Transcription, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Hogg, Jim (also includes Mary and Richard Medlin and Molly Thomas) - Tape, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hutton, Pat - Tape, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Johnson, Barbara Ann - Transcription, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Larronde, Nita and Kearney, Don - Tape, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Larronde, Nita and Kearney, Don - Transcription, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lee, Dan - Tape, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lee, Dan - Transcription, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - McCoy, Tim and Hoggett, Pat - Tape, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - McGee, Bob - Tapes (3), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - McGee, Bob - Transcription, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - McGee, Opal - Tapes (2), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - McGee, Opal - Transcription, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - McGee, Opal and Bob - Transcription, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - McKee, Maudie Bell - Tape, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - McKee, Maudie Bell - Transcription, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - McKee, Roy - Tape, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - McKee, Roy - Transcription, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - McKee, Sam - Tapes (2), 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - McKee, Sam - Transcription, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Norris, Rex and Granvil - Transcription, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Panks, Dan - Tapes (2), 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Panks, Dan - Transcription, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Roberts, Kathryn - Tapes (4, plus 1 with Granvil Norris), 1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Roberts, Kathryn - Transcription, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Shalbar, Colita - Transcription, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sibille, Stanley - Tapes (2), 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Williams, Bernadine, with Clifford, Page and Crystal - Transcription, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Williams, Calvin - Tape, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Williams, Calvin - Transcription, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified transcription, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Tape #1 Lester Jackson, Fred Gengehagel, Bernadine Williams, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Tape #2 [Blank], 1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Tape #3 Rudy Akin, Frank Elliot, Barbara Johnson, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Tape #4 Barbara Johnson, Molly Thomas, Arden and Josie Barney, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Tape #5 Barneys, Lola Albin, Russell LeGaudiet, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Tape #6 [no info], 1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Tape #7 [no info], 1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Notes from numbered Pie Town tapes, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - San Augustine, Texas, 1991
    - Brittain, James and Barbara - Tape, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Brittain, James and Barbara - Notes, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Bryan, Sheriff - Tape, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Bryan, Sheriff - Notes, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Clark, Ed - Tapes (2), 1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Clark, Ed - Transcriptions, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Dorsey, Ruby and Cornell - Tape (also includes Alford, Birdwell and Brewer), 1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Dorsey, Ruby and Cornell - Tape (also includes Lane, Leroy), 1991 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Dorsey, Ruby and Cornell - Tape (also includes Lane, Leroy, Ladner, Carolyn and Joe, and Oglesby), 1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Dorsey, Ruby and Cornell - Notes, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Goetz, Curt - Tape, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Goetz, Curt - Notes, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Grant, Jewell - Transcription, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Hardy, Ray - Tapes (3), 1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Hardy, Ray - Transcription, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Jackson, Michael - Transcription, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Ladner, Joe and Carol - Notes, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Lane, Leroy - Notes, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Lane, William and Ha - Notes, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Matthews, Woodrow - Transcription, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Mitchell, Rudy - Tapes (2), 1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Mitchell, Rudy - Notes, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Murpheys, and Tommy - Tapes (2) (also includes Pharmacist Bridges and Willie Mae Tendall), 1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Murpheys, and Tommy - Notes, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Nichols, Jack - Tape, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Nichols, Jack - Transcription, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Roberts, Kay - Tape, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Roberts, Kay - Transcription, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Ruth, Young William - Transcriptions (marked tape 5b), 1991 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Wade, Nelsyn - Tape, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Wade, Nelsyn - Transcription, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Whitton - Tapes (4), 1991 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Whitton - Transcription, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified transcription, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "San Augustine lecture – with Sam Malone, Lavonne Tendall, Willie Mae Tendall" (2 tapes), 1991 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "San Augustine" Tapes 1-2, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "San Augustine" Tapes 3-4, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - "San Augustine" Tapes 5-6, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - "San Augustine" Tape 7, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "Cruising San Augustine" (2 tapes), 1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Oral history tapes with no transcript, identified location, 1991
    - Hay, Arlan, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Martin, Maxie, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Murphy, Richard (2), 1991 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Piper, Sue and John, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Ray, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Revival, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Roberts, Tom, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Skillern, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - White Rock Tie and Lumber, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Videotapes, circa 1975, 1991
  Videotapes document the project by capturing the team members traveling and planning their progress, and by including some oral history work. These tapes are marked either "Pie Town" or "San Augustine", and are numbered. Additionally, one tape includes a thirty-minute interview with Russell Lee circa 1975, produced by Paul Hightower.
  - Russell Lee interview (black and white, poor quality, produced by Paul Hightower, 30 minutes, circa 1975), followed by unidentified color footage, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "Russell Lee #2 – Pie Town" (color), 1991 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Contents
    0-175 Hotel briefings; 176-898 Catherine McKee Roberts; 899-1081 Hotel in Pie Town; 1082-1180 Parade, Norris Town
  - "Russell Lee #3 – Pie Town" (color), 1991 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    0-377 Norris Ranch
    378-616 McKee Ranch
    617-1348 Molly at the dump
    1349-1801 Hogg Ranch
  - "Russell Lee #4 – Pie Town" (color), 1991 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    0-528 Hogg Ranch; 528-1130 Woody's house (fire); 1131-1683 McGee Ranch branding; 1726-1756 Pie Town canine; 1773 Goat folks
  - "San Augustine #1" (color), 1991 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    0-721 Murphy (County Clerk); 721-890 Francine C. and Eric W. on television; 891-1100 Kids on street; 1101-1126 Victorian house, churches; 1126 – James Brittain
  - "San Augustine #2" (color), 1991 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    0-342 James Brittain; 343-894 Barber shop; 894-1164 Saw mill; 1164-1719 Ray Kraft; 1719-1807 Verba Lee
  - "San Augustine #5" (color), 1991 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "San Augustine #6" (color), 1991 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Francine" (a copy of commercial videotape on New Zealand painter Colin McMahon), undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - "El Camino Real: The Royal Road to San Augustine" by Forrest Oglesbee, Eagle Scout Project, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "Reed Chapel Baptist Church [service], San Augustine", undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - "Rev. Fred Dade & China Chapel at the Sabine Valley Association at the Taylor Tabernacle, October, 1990" (color) (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Daguerre: The Birth of Photography" documentary, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Exhibit Catalogs, 1991-1992
  Exhibit Catalogs includes notes, drafts of the catalog text, page proofs, and one final copy.
  - Pie Town general notes, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Pie Town Intro notes, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 3-5)
  - Pie Town Summary (typescript photocopy), 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 6-7)
  - San Augustine Intro notes, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 8-9)
  - San Augustine Summary, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - General Summary Notes by Karen and Sondra, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Proofs, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Final copy, 1991-1992 (Box 13, Folder 13)
- Exhibit Panels, 1992 (Box 14, Box 15)
  Exhibit Panels include roughly the same text as is featured in the exhibit catalog, and are mounted on white mats.
- Photographs, 1991
  Photographs of Pie Town and San Augustine by Kathleen Dolan, Kerri Madden, Daryl Meyer, and Mark Edward Smith are included in this series. They are arranged by photographer in alphabetical order, then in groups featuring Pie Town and San Augustine.
  - Kathleen Dolan, 1991
    - Pie Town, New Mexico
      - Wedding Reception, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Near Pie Town, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Coonridge Farm, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Mr. Clark, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Lester Jackson, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Rosemary Hutton, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - House on Datil Highway, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Jim Hogg, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Rosemary Hutton's House, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Jim Hogg's residence, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - At the July Fourth Parade, (Quemado, NM), 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - [Woman with wolf people at grocery store], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - [Kearney girl], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Rex Norris and Granvil Norris, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Autumn Laurel Larronde Kearney, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Bernadine Williams, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Beatrice Crawford's Gate, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Wedding Reception Dance, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - San Augustine, Texas, 1991
      - Cecil Murphy, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - John Oglesbee, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Joe Ladner, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - [Reporter], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - [Leroy], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Arlen Hays, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Barber Shop, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Texaco Station, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Sheriff Charles Bryan, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Preacher's Son, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Mr. and Mrs. C. T. Dorsey, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Mike Jackson's House, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Leroy Lane, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Downtown Saturday, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Texaco Station, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Verba Lee's Family, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Verba Lee, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified Location - [Man repairing electric appliance], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Kerri Madden, 1991
    - Pie Town, New Mexico, 1991
      - Beatrice Crawford, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Interviewing Kathryn Roberts, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - John Piper, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Kathleen Dolan, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Nita Larronde and Autumn Laurel Kearney, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Water Wagons, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - San Augustine, Texas, 1991
      - Tom Roberts, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - True Vine Church, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - True Vine Church, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified Location - [Welding], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Unidentified Location - [Man under flag], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Darryl Meyer, 1991
    - Pie Town, New Mexico, 1991
      - Pie Town Post Office, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Pie Town Post Office, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Barbara Anne Johnson, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Tom Brannon, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Charles H. Hutzen, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - San Augustine, Texas, 1991
      - Liberty, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - First Methodist Church, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - First Methodist Church, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - After the Church Service, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified Location - [Hay bales], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified Location - [Man sitting by window], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Mark Edward Smith, 1991
    - Pie Town, New Mexico, 1991
      - Catarino Amaya, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Roy and Maudie Bell McKee, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Old Homesteader's Dugout, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Old Homesteader's Dugout, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Bob Magee Ranch, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Sombra del Gallo, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - The Barney House Under Construction, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - [Barney's House Construction], 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Paul Thomas' Old Cabin, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Lester Jackson's House, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Wes Hudson, Dan Lee, Melvin Hudson, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Wes Hudson, Dan Lee, Melvin Hudson, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Wes Hudson and Phil McKinley, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Old Pie Town Road, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Russell Smyth Interviewing Mike Hill, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Melvin "Cotton" Hudson, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Old Water Tower, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Sam McKee and Petie, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Vivian, Jeremiah, Catherine, and Jessie Bergkvist with Crystal and Sissy Williams, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Roy McKee's Garden, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Mike Hill, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Amber Lee Hudson, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Wes Hudson and Phil McKinley, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - San Augustine, Texas, 1991
      - Nelsyn's Furniture Store, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Nelsyn's Furniture Store, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Ace Hardware, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Ace Hardware, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Kay Roberts and Georgia May Roberts, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Kay Roberts and Georgia May Roberts, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - 7:50, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Nichols Family Reunion, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Mayor Curt Goetz, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Cattle Auction, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Future Home of the Museum, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - San Augustine Public Library, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Downtown Saturday, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - White Rock Logging Scale, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Sallie Whitton, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - First Methodist Church, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - San Augustine Livestock Market, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Josie Nichols, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Bogard Farms, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Bill Whitton, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Renfro Furniture Store, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Kay Roberts, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - White Rock Tie and Lumber, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Garner Family Reunion, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - San Marcos, Texas - Tom Anderson and Homero Garcia Interviewing Vista McCroskey, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 12)